<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>William Enckhausen</title>
    <link href="https://williamenck.art/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://williamenck.art" />
    <updated>2025-03-23T06:43:48-06:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>William Enckhausen</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://williamenck.art</id>

    <entry>
        <title>The Net</title>
        <author>
            <name>William Enckhausen</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://williamenck.art/the-net/"/>
        <id>https://williamenck.art/the-net/</id>

        <updated>2025-03-23T06:42:59-06:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    In some recent writings on this blog I have been attempting to comprehend the relationship betweeen the microcosm and the macrocosm through some practical stories of non-dualism. I wrote about situations not so much from the gaze of deep meditation or abstract contemplation but from&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <div class="html-div xdj266r x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r xexx8yu x4uap5 x18d9i69 xkhd6sd">
<div class="html-div xdj266r x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r xexx8yu x4uap5 x18d9i69 xkhd6sd" dir="auto">
<div class="html-div xdj266r x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r xexx8yu x4uap5 x18d9i69 xkhd6sd" data-ad-rendering-role="story_message">
<div id="«r78»" class="x1iorvi4 xjkvuk6 x1ye3gou xn6708d" data-ad-comet-preview="message" data-ad-preview="message">
<div class="x78zum5 xdt5ytf xz62fqu x16ldp7u">
<div class="xu06os2 x1ok221b">
<div class="xdj266r x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r x1vvkbs x126k92a">
<div dir="auto">In some recent writings on this blog I have been attempting to comprehend the relationship betweeen the microcosm and the macrocosm through some practical stories of non-dualism. I wrote about situations not so much from the gaze of deep meditation or abstract contemplation but from really mundane encounters in which the infinite light reveals itself in some really graceful and unexpected channels. One of my favorite metaphors for explaining the iterfusion <a class="html-a xdj266r x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r xexx8yu x4uap5 x18d9i69 xkhd6sd x1hl2dhg x16tdsg8 x1vvkbs" tabindex="-1"></a>of our human lives with the life of the living universe, or macrocosm, is the Hindu and Buddhist metaphor of the Net of Indra.</div>
<div dir="auto"> </div>
</div>
<div class="x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r x1vvkbs xtlvy1s x126k92a">
<div dir="auto">A scholar cited on the Wikipedia: "Far away in the heavenly abode of the great god Indra, there is a wonderful net which has been hung by some cunning artificer in such a manner that it stretches out infinitely in all directions. In accordance with the extravagant tastes of deities, the artificer has hung a single glittering jewel in each "eye" of the net, and since the net itself is infinite in dimension, the jewels are infinite in number. There hang the jewels, glittering "like" stars in the first magnitude, a wonderful sight to behold. If we now arbitrarily select one of these jewels for inspection and look closely at it, we will discover that in its polished surface there are reflected all the other jewels in the net, infinite in number. Not only that, but each of the jewels reflected in this one jewel is also reflecting all the other jewels, so that there is an infinite reflecting process occurring."</div>
<div dir="auto"> </div>
</div>
<div class="x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r x1vvkbs xtlvy1s x126k92a">
<div dir="auto">Beyond all of the bad intentions with all of the ads, political manipulations, and spying FB still has been a manner of conecting with other jewels in the net. Of course it is not the real thing, but if one connects with others from the deepest and noblest part of one´s being then even FB could serve as a medium of interconnection. Of course I would prefer other less manipulated software or spyware to mimic this interconnection, but this is where so many jewels in this planet are reflected. Playing with this metaphor of FB as the true Net,it is actually easier to understood its opposite: a place where all the reflections that penetrate one´s being actually make you less connected and more egocentric. One looks for and projects the most limited and fragmented reflections as each fine jewel is gradually dulled and pulverized into dust.</div>
<div dir="auto"> </div>
</div>
<div class="x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r x1vvkbs xtlvy1s x126k92a">
<div dir="auto">Yet beyond the digital mechanisms of interconnection there is the image or a few words from of an old friend sent out to other friends or perhaps directly to you. It makes me remember them in their essence. I see them in the present and I knew them from the past. There is still a connection. I see they are still shining brightly, flowing from the past into their future, growing and expanding, as microcosms unifying with the macrocosm.</div>
</div>
<div class="x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r x1vvkbs xtlvy1s x126k92a">
<div dir="auto">Yet this digital imitation of the Net often becomes becomes a little too stimulating, like too much coffee too late in the day. I find it difficult to sleep at night when I go into FB. It is the same if I go into an airport or a supermarket. All of those reflections that I encounter stay with me all through the night. It is usually not a negative experience. On the contrary it is quite positive in that there were positive interactions. Yet these jewels continue to shine through the night and Indra´s Net becomes more like a giant disco ball as everybody from the day is having a giant party in my room. Is this all too psychic or or just plain psychotic? And if I post a photo of myself then it is all the more intense, like drinking 3 cups of coffee and 5 in the afternoon. </div>
<div dir="auto"> </div>
</div>
<div class="x11i5rnm xat24cr x1mh8g0r x1vvkbs xtlvy1s x126k92a">
<div dir="auto">In the past I would delete a FB account when there were hacking attempts or when I got malware injected into my computer while logging in. That rarely happens nowadays and so I now have a <a href="https://www.facebook.com/william.enck.III/">Facebook account</a> that I share with readers of the blog.</div>
<div dir="auto"> </div>
<div dir="auto">The only tried and true communication software for me besides my email has been Telegram. I have the same account as I have always had and it has never been hacked. My Telegram username is @williamenck.  There are no ads nor tracking and it is open source software that can be publicly verified so as to not have any manipulations coded into the program. I do not have my own group nor do I use it a lot but it has always been an uninterrupted channel to maintain contact with others.  </div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>From Quetzalcoatl To Cassanova</title>
        <author>
            <name>William Enckhausen</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://williamenck.art/from-quetzalcoatl-to-cassanova/"/>
        <id>https://williamenck.art/from-quetzalcoatl-to-cassanova/</id>

        <updated>2025-03-11T19:10:58-06:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Human life is always at balance between inferiority and superiority complexes. We make so many mistakes based on such complexes, dominating others or submitting to the domination of others. However, one day we have to wake up, have true confidence and be more authentic without&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__image">Human life is always at balance between inferiority and superiority complexes. We make so many mistakes based on such complexes, dominating others or submitting to the domination of others. However, one day we have to wake up, have true confidence and be more authentic without these games of inferiority or superiority, without harming others and ourselves.<br><br>When one can see ones own mind without negative or positive prejudices or distortions one begins to see ones whole world without these distortions as well. One stops having opinions about other people’s characteristics and can really see what their minds are like with their past and present thoughts and emotions. All that the awakened mind sees are the dynamics of actions and reactions of minds. The previous actions have built a reality in the present and the actions of the present will create a reality for the future. It does not matter if one dies in debt of previous actions because they continue attached to the mind and the soul and seek to be reborn in the human body to pay those debts in another incarnation. Everything that one brings from genetic inheritance and the conditions of the environment of birth have been a result of previous actions, chosen by one. No one is the victim of an arbitrary chance. The conscious Macrocosm does not play dice as humans do. Some say that the soul always chooses its incarnations in the phase between death and rebirth. I think that this is so but also what the conscious macrocosm gives us precisely for balancing our previous actions, whether we want it and accept it or not. All who are incarnated on earth have debts with the universe and will be paid by us. In the end no one escapes the law of compensation, of action and reaction, or karma and samskara.<br><br>A yogi once stated that the power of spirit is so real that if one is bit by a poisonous snake but with firm determination says “I am not poisoned” then one will not become sick. Only because something is difficult to understand for the masses does not make it untrue. This yogi understood higher laws but the lot of humanity live in materialistic and deterministic ignorance. The discovery of higher psyco-spiritual laws make so many physical determinants vacuous and vaporous, and make our modern science shallow and our medicine so crude. I have seen so many times how so called incurable diseases like cancer and AIDS have been eradicated by a radical, spiritual change of consciousness. People gained a little bit of spiritual, vertical insight into their illness and understood the deeper reasons and were cured. Perhaps few can comprehend this but that does not make it untrue.<br><br>The physical world is a product of Spirit. We create realities based on our limited mental projections and these projections always bounce back as our karmic reactions and such frustrations only serve to strengthen these cognitive barriers. We continue believing that these personal and collective projections are absolute until some great clash awakens our spirit and broadens our mental projections. I am not saying that viruses, deadly illnesses or poisons are not real, only that they exist on a cruder plane of reality. Change the mind and you change the body. Change the mind and you change the world.<br><br>The key to a strong immune system is a strong mind. What is immunity but the ability of the organism to distinguish between what is me and what is not me? At the mental level this distinction of self and not self corresponds to moral discernment. One knows who one is and what are one´s personal boundaries. Most people are confused about such questions and simply let others decide what is best for them. They place too much faith in their pastors, their doctors or their favourite authors or even actors. A strong and insightful mind with discernment knows the inner labyrinths of the mind, the weaknesses and pitfalls of the self and therefore self deception is more difficult. So much mental confusion due to self ignorance creates a state of constant tension and stress and the physical immune system is also weakened by this lack of discernment.<br><br>Biopsychology is not an abstract and intellectual science for the tantric yogi. It is an intuitive science based on direct experience. One enters into the Anahata Vortex or Heart Chakra and becomes one with the heart of the universe. From this center one connects with the Aerial Factor, the subtle vibrations of prana that radiate through the entire universe. Every human mind is a potential portal for this connection if only the desires of the mind are purified from narrow-mindedness and selfishness. When the mind vibrates with universal love and spiritual union there is a warm glow in the chest. One feels the physical heart very calm and also feels the thymus gland as a very soft radiation of soothing energy. All internal sufferings are healed and the radiation from this mind also affects the Anahata Vortex and the organs corresponding to that vortex in other beings. The yogi becomes first at one with the universe and enters the universal heart and naturally radiates this calm to others.<br><br>In meditation we learn to bring the mind to a small point inside the pineal gland, so small it becomes infinitesimal. All contents of the mind are brought to this sacred space and handed over in simple confidence that they will be received.  Any fragmented and splintered part of the self brought into this space resounds back into spiritual life as resplendence.  This flow of thought from the finite mind into the infinite consciousness makes one more and more conscious and one actually becomes the witness consciousness. The mind gets lost in essence.  Consciousness is not an action of the mind but rather the essence of it.  The mind takes the ideation of pure and infinite consciousness and actually becomes pure and infinite consciousness. I become nothing and desire nothing as the Infinite being takes this mind back into its essence.  I let it worry about who I am and what I will do in this world.  All of the sorrows of life that are clearly reconciled with the infinite no longer bind one and joy begins to emerge from all of those once dark places.  The union of the mind with infinity is not a mere philosophical concept, but a lived experience in the eternal now.  Joy and the full acceptance of relative existence are the end product, the final proof of the evolution of our minds and selves towards pure and infinite Consciousness. <br><br>I have known yogis whose universal love and power of discernment was so strong that they could heal others. Their immunity was so strong that they could take on the weight of others. They were liberated from their own actions and reactions and lived freely united with the divine macrocosm. Some had the ability to heal others spiritually, taking their karmic reactions of others into their own mind so that others can advance on the spiritual path. Although they were saints and had a lot of spiritual grace accompanying them, they had to pay debts as if they were their own debts. Action and reaction are mechanical forces that even God cannot change. God only guides us how to get out of our web of karma and if God himself were to take human form to atone for our reactions, then god would have to pay the debt in flesh and blood as well. My yogi friends suffered a lot doing this work. In fact, they sacrificed their lives so that others could come out of the darkness. Some were stronger and able to move more people while others could only help a few people, but they did so with a force beyond the personal mind, or microcosmic mind. They had the grace to understand and use the forces of the Macrocosmic mind. However, they all suffered personally in this process even though they had the strength and spiritual perspective to endure the pain, not fall, and actually digest and transmute what they took from others. Living and studying with them, I saw this dynamic up close and asked many questions. My first book, A Name To The Nameless, was an attempt to explain the dynamics of the mind from this point of view, albeit abstracted from personal context and explained in the theoretical format of the psychology of tantra yoga. I tried to remove my personal opinions and experiences from the writing and focus on the psychological and spiritual processes of the mind. My purpose was to map the soul and mind to help others understand their patterns of action and reaction, or karma and samskara. My second book, Microvita And Tantra Maya, was more personal, in the first person, writing about personal experiences and my opinions. My third book, Light And Dark Tantra, is about my friends and teachers and the tragedy that happened when they died and their spiritual society lost their benevolent influence.<br><br>After one begins to meditate sincerely and feel that life is deeply full of meaning one understands that life is a process of liberation from emotional and cognitive bondages.  The individual is ultimately responsible for everything that happens and one´s inner attitudes and conditions determine what occurs in life.  It is no longer possible to blame anybody or anything for our existential and spiritual state of being when one begins to understand the law of action and reaction.  Instead, one is responsible for all of one´s past actions and the future requital of those actions and resigns to this universal law.  Only then can there be freedom, freedom from the past and freedom to act in the future without the cloudy disturbances of past complexes and fears distorting actions that generate negative reactions.  All spiritual people I know from all walks of life are on the path of this realization, no matter what their philosophies.  True spirituality connects one to the essence of life and the underlying spiritual laws that govern human existence and people who are aligned with the essence of their lives will always discover deeper, universal laws.  <br><br>If this understanding of self responsibility is realized to be true after one becomes spiritually mature, does it not also mean that the law of action and reaction was also active before one was aware of it?  All of the past suffering, inner chaos and disorder in life is not happenstance, but reactions to our previous actions.  It is a terribly heavy idea.  We often think of people as victims that have been treated unfairly in an unjust world where there is no real sense of order and justice.  And when the idea is presented that people are responsible for their own suffering sounds very cruel, like conservatives and racists that feel no sense of responsibility for  bettering the lives of the less fortunate.  I do not say that the law of karma should make one passive and insensitive to the suffering of others because "they deserve it, karmically."  Rather, it is to note that while trying to help other people it is important to understand that a part of their being is deeply tied to their suffering and to try to liberate it is to entangle oneself with something much more complex than a difficult personal history or tragic social injustices that harm one and inhibit personal growth.  There is also the mental pattern that one carries into these situations, certain attitudes and charged mental forces that resonate with these individual and social circumstances.  Some self-destructive "a priori" mental pattern accompanies their lived experiences, pre-disposing them to some suffering in life.<br><br>Teaching meditation to me was always a great joy, although very difficult at times.  Some people just needed a little instruction and guidance and they advanced very well by their own discipline and inspiration.  The good results of just a little discipline  inspired them onward in their spiritual practice.  Having the perspective of remaining in the "witness" state of consciousness as they learned in meditation helped them understand the clashes that life would inevitably bring their way.  They could see the deeper meaning of a situation and the lesson to be learned because they were able to stay in a calm center and this state of calmness always guided one intuitionally through a situation.  And with each clash there is greater cohesion in the inner mind and an understanding of the laws of the mind and spirit.  Everybody gets stuck now and then but a good meditator usually finds the answers they need in their meditation but also by associating with like-minded people in a similar path.  We are all much more similar than different and people with a little more experience and time on the spiritual path can share their experiences with others to help guide them forward.  <br><br>Teaching people who are already in the process of "self-actualization" is all too easy.  They take on their own existential burdens.  However, not many people advance so easily.  Most carry more baggage and this is always more work for the teacher.  Many people need help and seek relief for their existential maladies, but not everybody is ready to go deeply into themselves via tantra yoga or other really strong approaches to meditation and spiritual discipline.  This is only possible by combining a lot of psychotherapy techniques along with the spiritual practices.  Some people may need something akin to therapy, others just need to talk and address their issues with a trusted guide, while some people just need to be inspired by some good ideas.  When one is in a spiritual society it is important that there is a culture of spirituality available to all with sufficient emotional and intellectual tools for the community.  <br><br>Unfortunately, this is where things become very difficult and where so many spiritual societies end up becoming religions or cults.  Instead of having effective techniques of spiritual practice there enter ideas of inclusiveness and privilege for those on the inside.  They follow behind some charismatic leader and instead of really doing their own inner work, they take refuge in the prestige of the teacher or their group.  They may learn the spiritual lingo and repeat it like parrots while trying to make an impression on newcomers.  Here, one simply develops the same prejudices in mundane social life that make the ego feel superior or empowered.  The underlying sense of inferiority is covered up by self aggrandizement but these complexes are never really transmuted.  Eventually all of these masks will fall and one is left even more lost and confused.  <br><br><br><img loading="lazy"  src="https://williamenck.art/media/posts/43/9.jpg" alt="" width="1024" height="768" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://williamenck.art/media/posts/43/responsive/9-xs.jpg 640w ,https://williamenck.art/media/posts/43/responsive/9-sm.jpg 768w ,https://williamenck.art/media/posts/43/responsive/9-md.jpg 1024w ,https://williamenck.art/media/posts/43/responsive/9-lg.jpg 1366w ,https://williamenck.art/media/posts/43/responsive/9-xl.jpg 1600w ,https://williamenck.art/media/posts/43/responsive/9-2xl.jpg 1920w"></figure><br><br>After 2012 and my writings about the narco war more people wanted to come into contact with me.  I was like a hermit who hardly left the desert where I had built my home and a small community.  I was working with an indigenous healer who saw herself as my manager and was jealous of anybody who became close to me, people who became my students and friends. Although quite an intuitive and effective healer, her emotional insecurities eventually got the best of her.<br><br>My friend was a very influential person with the Zapatistas.  She was deeply distressed by the sexual misconduct of the male leaders in the movement, namely those of Subcomandante Marcos.  She began to have deep resentments towards men, especially men in situations of power who had attractive qualities.<br><br>Also, the situation with a yoga society she was involved with started going down quickly.  I had left that society long ago but she still had some associations with them.  All we encountered were criminal and sexual scandals.  She became enraged over this and often her rage carried over to me, and perhaps even all men.  I became all the more the playboy in her mind each time she heard of these monastic scandals.  Later, when we began to encounter homosexual scandals with the monks, she really lost control. She never expressed hatred toward gays before this but later started to see homosexuals around every corner, and eyed them with hatred. <br><br>Eventually she started telling me that a group of students who are doctors helping the rural communities of Chiapas were really a band of sexual perverts and basically behaved like a group of Roman senators in togas.  This was her effort to get me to despise them.  I found it hard to believe.  Later, she started to accuse me of perversions and saying I was trying to manipulate people sexually.  Yet at the same time she went around praising me and telling people I was the incarnation of Quetzalcoatl.<br><br>I can sympathize with her anger toward "machismo" within and without of her yoga society.  I did not like it either.  It provoked a lot of repulsion in me too.  Repulsion is a subtle tendency (at the Vishuddha level).  Essentially, it is a protection of one´s discernment (Viveka) and keeps harmful expressions away.  There may be moral grounds to feel repulsion toward immoral activities that truly cause harm to people, yet one has to be careful not to fall into hatred.  Then, one´s heightened sense of morality can indeed become an expression of immorality if one begins to judge and slander other people.  Once hatred has taken hold of the mind then enters fear and paranoia.  To entertain such negative ideas and emotions in the mind actually makes the mind resonate with these energies.  Mind has the peculiar quality to become one with its objects of attachment.  The same negativity that one attaches to becomes part of one´s own mind. <br><br>Due to this I was forced to try and understand something I had not given a lot of effort to understanding.  I also saw many homosexual expressions as something really imbalanced, however, I really did not see them as so much different than heterosexual hyper sexuality in the form of "free love" and open sexual relationships.  Whether heterosexual or homosexual these sexual indulgences always create more suffering than pleasure and cause degeneration.  Unlike her, I could not condemn them but I tried to see their higher consciousness beyond their impulses and distortions.  One must understand that our social world is degenerated with so much narcissism, hedonism, materialism and hyper sexuality that create so many psychological complexes.  Also, I saw that there were more mature and responsible homosexuals that contained their sexual expressions with other homosexuals in a more responsible manner.  How could I condemn them if these homosexuals were even more responsible than heterosexuals who practiced the hypocrisy of "free love" and went around harming others with their selfish impulses? Yet on the other hand I cannot assert, as some religious homosexual activist do, that God simply made them that way.  I think if God were to create  homosexuals or guide evolution creatively, then such a God would have given more appropriate organs for homosexual expressions, especially with male homosexuals who practice sodomy.  The anus is simply an excretory organ that is not divinely designed for healthy sexual activity.  I certainly believe that divine compassion is for all and that God does not judge anybody for anything, but that homosexuality just like other human mental adjustments and complexes are of our own making, our own history of karmic actions and reactions. God has nothing to do with the creation of homosexuality yet divine compassion can touch and transform all parts of our being. <br><br>Also, some of her followers had certain homosexual confusions.  I saw them as heterosexuals with slight homosexual tendencies.  Intuitionally, I saw their minds had some strong complexes in the second chakra, the svadhistana.  I always saw that male homosexuals had two very strong propensities in the svadhistana:  lack of confidence and compulsion.  These emotional and energetic imbalances distort the svadhistana´s libido, cause the pranic or energetic flow of the mind to move downward (toward the first chakra), and overstimulate the first chakra by creating the confusion that the anus is an erogenous zone.  In the case of people with slight homosexual tendencies, they often resolved their homosexual tendencies by seeing these underlying complexes in their minds with the help of meditation, yoga exercises and the study of yogic bio psychology.  It certainly was not easy to become aware of such unconscious tendencies rooted in the base of the personality and it was a lot of work on my part to guide them through the process, but I did see that these people eventually became heterosexuals with healthy relationships.  This is a process much more refined than the "Pray The Gay Away" dogmas that harmed many people by making them more repressed and guilty about a homosexuality that never disappeared or was successfully transmuted into heterosexuality.  I saw that many people could become completely heterosexual by processing their complexes in the svadhistana, but not all.  <br><br>In short, I always tried to treat homosexuals as I do other people.  If they express sexual imbalances then I try not to see it as so different than heterosexual imbalances.  If they are more mature, conscious, and responsible I simply recommended monogamy and a mature, compassionate relationship just as I recommend to heterosexuals.  <br><br>Spiritual practice with yogic meditation depends so much upon understanding yoga psychology which also includes bio-psychology. Bio-psychology in this sense is understanding how the non material mind acts in synchronicity with the material body. It is not just the abstract understanding of how the mind connects with the glands and organs of the body but rather a practical understanding of this science with the end of bringing tranquility to the mind. In order to calm the mind it is necessary to confront one´s bio-psychological complexes, the unconscious drives and impulses that affect one´s peace of mind. Meditation is not an escape from these complexes. Meditation is the cure for all existential complexes. In the beginning of this process the mind is working more with biological desires and fundamental existential issues like self worth and establishing a positive self image by keeping the mind in a healthy and balanced state that is full of purpose and meaning. Without confronting the blind impulses one remains stuck in them and adjusts life according to their governance, which in the end is but “a raging bundle of desire in a dying animal.”<br><br>Instead of studying biology or endocrinology a yogi uses the mind to consciously reflect upon the body. Mental blockages also have bio-psychological “energetic” blocks which can be understood and also acted upon by the contemplative mind. According to yoga psychology the mind uses the brain as its seat and moves throughout the central nervous system. It has several nexus with the physical body in places where the nervous system branches out of the spinal column to control the glands and organs of the body. Traditionally, these centers have been called “chakras.” Yogis consider them whirling vortexes of subtle energy that the concentrated mind can perceive and feel and even influence with concentrated thinking and imagination. I prefer to call these centers “vortexes” because the word chakra now has so many flaky new age dogmas attached to it. I wrote “A Name To The Nameless” as an attempt to explain my understanding of these centers and how to develop the mind body system in the practice of yogic mediation.<br><br>Understanding sexuality is essential to peace of mind and spiritual development. Human psychological issues are rooted in our relationship with other people and we seek to have deeper relationships with other humans the more we grow and develop. Of course when there is a sexual element in these relationships they become all the more complex.<br><br>Modern biology has a developed understanding of how testosterone effects brain development. Not only is it responsible for sexual desires but it is also related to aggression. Yoga psychology recognizes this as well but also proposes that a properly balanced second “chakra” or “svadhistana” vortex (which corresponds to the genital organs) also helps one develop the foundations of self confidence and rationality. A balanced second vortex (svadhistana means self-establishment) expresses balanced sexuality and with self confidence and rationality established within the personality there is less need of the self defense mechanism of aggression. An imbalanced second chakra is fixated on sexuality with all kinds of psychological complexes propelling sexual behavior. Sometimes people use sex to cover insecurities or express aggression and domination while others are ignorant of other pleasures and indulge in sexuality as if it were the only true desire in life. The imbalanced second chakra is the root of machismo or toxic masculinity. Only humans who do the work of deep self reflection and take moral responsibility for their blind impulses can make any spiritual advancement. The reason why spirituality is so rare on the planet is because most people still have not resolved their fundamental sexual and self confidence issues.<br><br>I already wrote A Name To The Nameless as a theoretical structure. When I think of that old work I often relate those ideas with the life I have lived and the people whom I have met since then. A friend once suggested that I write a practical commentary for this theoretical work. Maybe this is the beginning of the endeavor?<br><br>Revisiting the second or “svadhistana” vortex reminds me of how I once met a follower of this healer, an educated young man who thought my neutered donkey who still chased around the lady donkeys might have miraculously grown a new pair. He had very high qualifications while he was in high school and so I thought he was joking but he actually believed it. I told him to examine the donkey and see if he could find the new pair. Obviously, he could not, but he said that perhaps some pieces of his testicles maintained within. I mockingly said that perhaps he originally really had three jewels and the veterinarian with his preconceived ideas only removed two and one actually remained to continue fueling those wild donkey desires. He said “maybe so.” Such was his desperation to affirm his belief in some transcendental reality where miracles are possible. He was an attractive young man with a lovable personality but he struggled to find a girl friend. I knew he had romantic longings but something inside of him either shut out or was afraid of expressing himself and his feelings toward women.<br><br>I always suspected that his issues were related with what Sigmund Freud called “castration anxiety,” the anxiety and fear of what will happen to him if he becomes vulnerable by letting this inner part of him out into some form of expression. Castration is symbolic of having your desires cut off from full expression by the fear of rejection. I think his fanciful ideas were fueled by his sexual repressions. Some people thought he was a closet case homosexual.  Some very potent and valid need inside of him needed to mature so as to liberate his mind from this tension so that his rationality could develop more completely so that the head and heart are equally balanced. His wild ideas only became more sound and grounded when he found a female companion years later. In the beginning of his awakening I could see an animal desire awakening within him and instead of being timid he became a little too cocky and assertive. The animal was reconciling itself with the human. Fortunately, love was governing his development and these expressions seemed to be just and adjustment to some newly awakened force within him.<br><br>People have so many wishes with biases and preconceived conceptions and seek to have them affirmed by outside sources, whether they are UFOs, conspiracy theories, or somebody who believes in X-File cases of miraculous donkey testicle regrowth. With irrationality the mind is desperately trying to impose some kind of meaningful order upon the inner chaos of uncertainty and self doubt. Anything that contradicts these biases are simply ignored. Sometimes they are laughable cases and seem innocent and harmless. But what happens when this fantasy bias is transferred into other aspects of existence, into one´s religious or political beliefs, motivating one to rally behind some politician, believe in conspiracy theories, or affirm a belief in some god and scriptures? This is where comedy becomes tragedy and where depth psychology is necessary as a tool to help humanity discover what forces actually guide our minds.<br><br>Is the same structure of irrational belief behind the casting of the vote or one´s attendance in church? The difference is just a difference in degree and not in kind. People from the Heaven´s Gate cult were all well educated computer programmers. They could perform complex logical cognitive activities by maintaining computer systems while at the same time follow a nut case guru that convinced them to castrate themselves and commit collective suicide before being beamed up into a passing comet! I suspect that even the most elaborate belief systems have something of this biased fantasy element to some degree or another and that only existential insecurity and a lack of confidence in oneself (a castrated confidence) maintain them. And for so long do we keep the flame of hope glowing through all of the scandals and contradictions that emerge from these bio-psychological projections. <br><br>Once there was a young woman with AIDS.  She was in the clinic for a few days and interacting with us.  She behaved like a perfect lady toward me.  Near her I felt really heavy and dirty inside my mind, like I had been living a totally different life than my own.  The young woman began to feel better and believed that I was helping her.  I personally had very little interaction with her but the healer told her that it was I who was indeed helping her.  Later, she was cured and began to change her life-style.  On other occasions there were other young women with emotional and sexual problems that affected their internal feminine organs.  It was very strange and interesting to see inside of their minds, to resonate with organs that I do not have.  Again, I felt a little heavy for a few days but these people always healed and changed their lives.  I hardly ever interacted with these people because the work was so heavy and I knew that they had a lot of gratitude and could project a lot of emotional transference toward me.  In the beginning the healer always said that I was doing the work of the guru and that I was even the incarnation of Quetzalcoatl!  Later, she would become jealous of people`s respect for me and I went from being Quetzalcoatl to Casanova, and instead of healing their internal organs she said I was actually manipulating their external feminine organs.  <br><br>There are many hidden powers along the path of mental-spiritual evolution, and also many hidden dangers.  Sometimes when a spiritual aspirant has a potent mind and an honest personality he or she is tested with a little occult power.  Because truth can be seen a little more clearly through a developed mind such a developed mind is given the capacity to see even more truth.  Perhaps they begin to see the future of people or see into the suffering of their minds and have the ability to even heal others.  Initially this endowment of mental force by the Macrocosm is for the sake of individual and collective evolution.  The more one advances on the spiritual path the more personal sacrifice is required.  Really, it is not sacrifice when there remains little selfish desire and one truly seeks the welfare of others.  However, no evolutionary process is entirely complete and one must always struggle to remove limitations.  If during the development of psychic powers there still remains some self-centred desire, then these powers may become a very dangerous obstacle and even a cause for spiritual downfall.<br><br>My friend got into trouble when she became a channeller.  Her information was always surprisingly accurate.  She could know secret details about the private lives of her patients.  Time and time again she was right on the mark.  I believe this worked for her when she was only channelling one strong microvita, or disencarnate spiritual force.  However, with time she began to channel other forces.  At the same time she became more famous and her ego became too powerful and imperious.  Gradually, she began to lose her power and her mental equilibrium, a form of psychic schizophrenia like a wizard trapped in a tower.  Fortunately, she lost her power before she entirely lost her mind.  It is a blessing that the Macrocosm takes occult power away from people when they misuse it.  <br><br>I began to learn about microvita, or discarnate spiritual force, while studying with Chidghananda in India.  In the process of healing one may connect with certain microvita in order to get information on how to heal another mind.  This information and spiritual force is useful in that the distorted mental patterns that create physical illness do not affect the healer.  This is not the same as channelling.  Channelling is when one opens one´s mind as a vehicle for discarnate force and one´s will is suspended while the will of the microvita takes temporary control of the mind and body.  Channelling is always a dangerous and inferior healing process that eventually creates mental imbalances.  A strong healer does not succumb to the "possession" of the spiritual force that helps in the process, nor does the strong healer succumb to the mental patterns that create illness in the mind of the one being healed.  Instead, a spiritual healer connects to the information and force of microvita to use it in the process of healing.  This proper use of spiritual force helps diminish the influence of the negative patterns of the mind being healed upon the mind of the healer.   <br><br>Spiritual healing and working with microvita is not so much different in principle than leadership in the mundane social world.  A leader must be open and receptive to his or her subordinates.  One must be understanding and take into account all opinions.  However, a leader must have the strength to make decisions based on a greater discernment and insight that, while being considerate to all opinions, must have the strength to decide and override divergent aims when the decisive moment arrives.  A weak leader may be too influenced by all of the voices one hears and cannot make clear decisions because one wants to please everybody and has no strong resolve.  Similarly, a weak healer may be overcome by the influences of the infirm mental patterns and may become ill while trying to transmute them.  The weak healer may also invoke a discarnate force or microvita to do the healing work through their own mind and body.  Ramakrishna made a very relevant analogy when referring to a weak guru as a small serpent trying to swallow a fish but cannot and both the serpent and the fish are stuck in a process of suffering.  The serpent cannot swallow and the fish remains squirming in its jaws.  A strong guru is one who can swallow it in one bite.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>A Greeting</title>
        <author>
            <name>William Enckhausen</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://williamenck.art/a-greeting/"/>
        <id>https://williamenck.art/a-greeting/</id>

        <updated>2025-03-11T19:10:12-06:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    A really evil person sent me a good vibration the other day. I did not realise that he had such a bad vibe when I first saw him smiling at me and nodding his head to say hello. People around here are generally very friendly&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>A really evil person sent me a good vibration the other day. I did not realise that he had such a bad vibe when I first saw him smiling at me and nodding his head to say hello. People around here are generally very friendly and strangers often say hello to me. He had a friendly expression that I connected with just before I realised he looked like a narco paramilitary with a bald head, long beard and was covered in tattoos up to his neck. Maybe it is just his style, I thought. Then I saw he was towing a crashed Volvo. Then I knew he must be a narco because who else in this part of Mexico could have a Volvo? I have never seen a Volvo around here. Also, there never used to be any men around here that looked like that. Nowadays, they are more common. They do not always carry rifles but sometimes do.<br><br>Anyway, strange encounters….I just went on with my day. However, I began to have a terrible headache and felt some really evil energy enveloping me. It lasted into the night and I could not sleep. Apparently, there was not much to think about. I did not have any fear of this person or what he represented. It was truly remarkable that this person who had the mental energy of a killer could also have a friendly side. It was an interesting contradiction and an interesting encounter to tell my friends and family about, but not something that should be keeping me up at night.<br><br>When affected by strange energies that leave me sleepless I practice creative imagination, an exercise that I hope will activate the subconscious to touch and interpret these disturbing energies. If there is some insight then there is peace of mind. Comprehension helps to assimilate the meaning of why such an occurrence happened and what it means internally, in the psychic and spiritual dimensions. Such an event might seem random to the sensory-intellectual mind but may be something very significant if seen with intuition. An intuitive understanding of what has happened makes the mind straight as an arrow again and the headache disappears. I am not really meditating as i am lying down trying to sleep. I almost fall asleep but am interrupted by a quick and vivid dream image or an idea that flashes into my mind. It gives me a piece to the puzzle. I would rather fall asleep but I cannot and must play energetic detective and let the spirit work its mysteries out to the questioning mind. Therefore, I just lay awake waiting for intuition to fill in all of the gaps.<br><br>The last thoughts I had before sleeping were very meaningful and eventually helped me sleep. I remembered how recently I was invited to attend a child´s first communion ceremony in a local church. Like so many times in the past I scoffed at that old institution and recalled how I once said I would never step into a church but more often I would find really nice people and good vibes from Catholics. I just accepted it as a contradiction in life. This time was no different. News just broke out a few years ago about the Church´s murder of indigenous children in Canada that they had secretly buried. Tribal members were still waiting for an apology from the Pope. I do not know if they ever got it, but if they did it came far too late.<br><br>I once became friends with a Catholic Father in Chiapas. He wanted me to teach him meditation. He had a very open mind and a sincere heart. He was truly serving his community with a good Christian spirit. Yet he was very stressed because his clerical superior was the owner of a few brothels and had many political and narco connections. I understand that fathers confess to each other. He treated me as one of his own even though he knew I was not Catholic or even Christian. I heard his confession and then he slept. It was one of the craziest situations that I had ever heard of.<br><br>I went into the church with these ideas fresh in my mind. However, there was a good vibration and the people seemed sincere. The priest´s sermon was on Christian forgiveness. He mentioned the recent violence and the terror that people were living through with all of the conflicts of the narco wars. He said that we must pray for even the wicked and misguided people as well. He was very sincere and I thought that to really be able to do that one must really have a high degree of inner peace and living wisdom. Most people were probably too terrified to be able to send compassion to the terrible. One must truly have a source of peace and love to make such prayers. Once again I was struck by this great contradiction. “Está cabrón, esa situación. Siempre encontrando las obras del Cabrón Divino.”<br><br>And as I lie awake I finally get my answer. Who knows who that narco who nodded at me is? Was he forced into conscription by the cartel? Was he just desperate and poor and made a bad choice by voluntarily joining. His cartel was able to get the support from our community because they were keeping out a much more ruthless and violent cartel from entering here. They never bothered the common people but the other cartel started to extort all of the local businesses. The “good” cartel told the locals that if they supported them they would keep out the “bad” cartel. The community accepted a parasitic relationship with the lesser evil. Maybe this death soldier was just happy to be at peace in a place where he did not, at least for the time being, have to kill people and wanted a respite of harmony with the local community? Who knows. This is such a crazy planet with such crazy people. Maybe even god is crazy. Yet there is love and forgiveness and healing in the universe. Could even a narco be touched by this? Who is to judge if we all come from the same essence? The only way I can remain an optimist is because there is obviously a spark of the divine in the human conscience. Upright individuals are always better than corrupt institutions whether it is a narco who wants a little peace or a priest who is a true and sincere Christian yet remains in a Catholic cartel.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Joy And Trauma</title>
        <author>
            <name>William Enckhausen</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://williamenck.art/joy-and-trauma/"/>
        <id>https://williamenck.art/joy-and-trauma/</id>

        <updated>2025-03-11T19:09:17-06:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    A few years ago a Facebook friend who turned out to not be very friendly made some comments on some photos of me playing the flute in some indigenous community in Chiapas. She said that I played classical music that those people probably could not&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>A few years ago a Facebook friend who turned out to not be very friendly made some comments on some photos of me playing the flute in some indigenous community in Chiapas. She said that I played classical music that those people probably could not understand. I told her I played the music that I personally like, beautiful and contemplative melodies that I find very spiritual and that can be played on a solo instrument. I told her it was not like I was playing Schoenberg or Stockhausen or some abstract music in which you need some modern (perhaps warped) sense of aesthetics to appreciate. I often got into friendly debates with my musician friends who were into more modern currents of music. I would ask why even a mind uneducated in music can find a melody of Bach or Mozart very beautiful but who would have a melody of Stockhausen repeating itself in one´s mind? You would have to be either insane or very abstracted from natural aesthetics and caught up in abstract, 20th century concepts of art to find some kind of beauty in that music. That is an extreme example, of course. Yet many people who are educated and from the "first world" cannot follow a much more approachable work of Beethoven or Mozart without getting bored or sleepy.<br><br>When I first arrived to Jaltenango I used to go and meditate and play flute by the river in the afternoons. I had many friendly interactions while doing so. Children and adults would come up and say hello and say they liked the music and wanted to see my flute. Once there was a man who would bring me mangoes from his ranch near the river when he heard me playing by the river. He had several varieties of mangoes that he would bring me and I would return to share them with my friends. We became friends with a few conversations. One day he asked more about my past and so I also asked him where he was from. I knew that most of the people in this region came from indigenous communities in Chiapas after the government started some land distribution programs in the 1950s. Most people had lost their indigenous roots, spoke only Spanish, and had entered into mainstream, marginalised Mexican culture. I guessed from his age that he did not grow up in Jaltenango.<br><br>What he told me was unforgettable. He was from an indigenous community of Chiapas. At 13 years of age his family sold him to a rancher where he was abused and overworked. He remained a slave until he was 16, considered independent and old enough to be set free. He said he worked hard and was able to buy a piece of land and start a life. He had passed through alcoholism and seemed to have an existential insight of how his past traumas drove him toward alcoholism. A few years before this I heard an account that helped me begin to understand the existential situation of so many indigenous people. I was at the CIDECII, an indigenous cooperative university in San Cristobal. A Zapatista leader was speaking about this subject of modern slavery, of how families were so poor that they sold their children to ranchers. I gathered she had passed through such a situation. She seemed to be a very wise, strong and admirable maternal figure that many people trusted. She said that being mistreated, physically, and/or sexually abused was so common with indigenous children who were sold into slavery. It was so common that it has become a core issue in the collective story of modern indigenous people.<br><br>After hearing his story I put myself in his place and could easily imagine how easy it would be to get lost in some addiction as a way to cope with such overwhelming traumas. Recalling it is personally a great trauma but also a great joy. It makes me feel miserable about the human condition but also gives one hope that all things may be healed. What would I be like if I had passed through such traumas: a street fighter, a schizophrenic, heroin junkie or just an alcoholic? It was inconceivable. What was even more inconceivable is how warm and loving this man was despite his past difficulties. I have found this paradox in so many of my indigenous friends and have admired their strong hearts.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Gymnopedia On Yerba Mate</title>
        <author>
            <name>William Enckhausen</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://williamenck.art/gymnopedia-on-yerba-mate/"/>
        <id>https://williamenck.art/gymnopedia-on-yerba-mate/</id>

        <updated>2025-03-11T19:08:20-06:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I play the solo quenacho flute to aid contemplation, to cure a headache and sometimes in my yoga classes during the relaxation. Recently, while travelling, a person was listening to me play by the beach. She was very grateful and told me that she had&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>I play the solo quenacho flute to aid contemplation, to cure a headache and sometimes in my yoga classes during the relaxation. Recently, while travelling, a person was listening to me play by the beach.  She was very grateful and told me that she had been depressed and that the music made her feel better.  I was playing what I remembered from Satie's Gymnopedia.  I knew most of it by heart, but there were some parts I had forgotten.  I decided to memorise the piece.  In my yoga classes (which I plan to restart shortly) I like to play music spontaneously, but once in a while it's nice to play a serene piece by a great composer.  I decided to record this piece to see what it sounded like when I listened to it.  I used my heartbeat to keep the tempo.  It's a little faster than normal because I had a strong cup of yerba mate before recording.</p>
<p><br><a href="https://soundcloud.com/user-227830798/gymnopedia-i-satie?utm_source=clipboard&amp;utm_medium=text&amp;utm_campaign=social_sharing">Gymnopedia </a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Apparitions</title>
        <author>
            <name>William Enckhausen</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://williamenck.art/apparitions/"/>
        <id>https://williamenck.art/apparitions/</id>

        <updated>2025-03-11T19:06:34-06:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    "The apparition of these faces in the crowd: Petals on a wet, black bough." After travelling through two international airports in one day I recall Pound´s "In A Station Of The Metro." Sleepless, I lie awake at night seeing all of the faces of the&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>"The apparition of these faces in the crowd:<br>Petals on a wet, black bough."<br><br>After travelling through two international airports in one day I recall Pound´s "In A Station Of The Metro."  Sleepless, I lie awake at night seeing all of the faces of the day, even the one´s I never remembered even seeing pass by because I did not continue to think about them.  Yet I remember them at night, all at once in my room for a giant party.  <br><br>"We are one and I am always with you.  We see the Eminent in every face," the guru once told me.  More than a command of the guru it was a demand to perceive and conceive correctly.  To not see the infinite in the finite, the Macrocosm in the microcosm, is an error of perception for the microcosm.  Not seeing the divinity of another being is a spiritual shortcoming.  Recalling that experience makes me remember that we part of one great soul and I am not a lonely madman lying awake sleepless at night.  I was in a worldly hurry and did not perceive and conceive correctly.    Well, if this sleepless night is some sort of trip then let us make it the best.  I wish you all infinite love and now I will get some rest.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Redemption</title>
        <author>
            <name>William Enckhausen</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://williamenck.art/redemption/"/>
        <id>https://williamenck.art/redemption/</id>

        <updated>2025-03-11T19:05:58-06:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    A mystic seeks some higher, absolute and enduring truth and declares the world as something that must be transcended. Suffering the loss of what is near and dear in the relative, ever-changing world propels more conscious beings to renounce blind attachments and fleeting desires to&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p><br>A mystic seeks some higher, absolute and enduring truth and declares the world as something that must be transcended.  Suffering the loss of what is near and dear in the relative, ever-changing world propels more conscious beings to renounce blind attachments and fleeting desires to find something higher, or at least relate to what is relative and temporal in a more sensible and compassionate manner.  Reading the works of sages and mystics of East and West one finds two main and opposing views of the relative, created world.  Some see is as something to be renounced and never to look back upon while others see it as something to turn back to because it is redeemable and there is some deep meaning to be realised within it.  The former tend to be pessimistic philosophies and often remove one from any joy in existence.  <br><br>I have had a few friends on the spiritual path who, when they were suffering some great loss or frustrated desire, chose the nihilistic outlook even though they had some spiritual understanding.  "Yes the spirit is real but this world is just suffering and there is no happiness here."   I recently told one such friend that he was denying the validity of the world but at the same time was making his demands upon god to fulfil his desires here.  When it does not work out and when god cannot be extolled, then god becomes some kind of wicked entity working against him.  I said that some god is not to blame for the frustration of relative desires that are already based in suffering and separateness.  A desperate being with some blind impulse wants to impose his desires on the world and when it does not work out there is even greater despair and god is to blame?  The mind alienated from Consciousness is so shrewd and powerful and manipulates in so many ways.  What else but chaos could possibly manifest when it is driven by blind, unconscious impulses?  Might it have been different is the desire was more conscious and if one checks to see if the Tao, or intelligent force behind the universe, is backing up such a desire.<br><br>The supreme consciousness is within us.  It is evolving through us.  Our lives are so much greater than we can possibly conceive.  Each life is the result of billions of years of evolution through so many forms of life- plant, reptile, animal- their DNA is within us and our DNA is simply stacked on top of theirs.  Where did this impulse come from and where is it going?  Humans gave a clearly reflected consciousness.  We can ask ourselves where our consciousness comes from, from where the notion of "I exist" has its origins.  Mystics of all times and places have realised the perennial philosophy of the union of the individual soul with the supreme soul.  There is no escape from human existence and the relative world.  Blind impulse only binds one toward suffering while attempting to escape the world also creates suffering and emptiness.  To find union with the infinite one must move with life and evolution and flow toward the One.  <br><br>I am on the side of optimism regarding the relative world.  Being here in time and space and on this planet at this point in time is important and it has a great purpose that is capable of being understood.  One can discover the laws of existence in the universe and walk in harmony with them.  Certainly there are desires that are a complete waste of time and only lead to degeneration (perhaps the majority of them in this materialistic time).  However, one´s truest desires are one what needs to evolve and eventually reach the spirit.  If spirit is behind life and evolution then spirit will take care of and fulfil such desires.  If one seeks a love that is to truly unify with others and make oneself more whole, then such a desire will be fulfilled by spirit because they are eventually for the realisation of the spirit.  The infinite unity of spirit can be expressed in the relative world by love and compassion towards all beings.  If one seeks a lower form of impulsive, selfish love and is frustrated and despairs, then that is actually a good thing. It was an impossible situation, anyway.  Hopefully, one can realise how suffering is a self-spun invention, let go and be led.  </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Inward Mirror</title>
        <author>
            <name>William Enckhausen</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://williamenck.art/the-inward-mirror/"/>
        <id>https://williamenck.art/the-inward-mirror/</id>

        <updated>2025-03-11T19:00:02-06:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I had just gotten off of the train in Berlin. I was waiting for a friend who had been talking to two German girls and was exchanging addresses with them. While waiting for him a punk with a blue mohawk approaches me and asks if&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>I had just gotten off of the train in Berlin.  I was waiting for a friend who had been talking to two German girls and was exchanging addresses with them.  While waiting for him a punk with a blue mohawk approaches me and asks if I had a cigarette.  I did not understand German but understood his gesture.  I said "no" in English and he understood I was not German.  He asked me in perfect English where I was from and we started chatting.  Although he looked a little coarse he was actually a really friendly and intelligent person.  He asked me if I liked punk rock.  I said I knew very little of it but my uncle gave me a Sex Pistols cassette a few years ago when I was sixteen and I really enjoyed it.  It was not really music that moved my soul or was beautiful but the Sex Pistols were very humorous in their audacity and rebellion.  He started to sing some lines from "God Save The Queen". ......"God save The Queen.....the fascist regime.....they made you a moron.....and there is no future for you in England's dreaming.....". And then started to shout the refrain "no future, no future for you" at the people passing by.  Although a little embarrassed I found it humorous.  <br>I remarked that his English was so good because he listened to English punk music.  He said that God Save The Queen was a great manifesto for him.  Punks did not really  hate people, just their false institutions created by false pretty and princely people who screw everybody else.  He was sincere and well spoken and I liked his perspective but my friend came and interrupted our conversation.  <br><br>I had been travelling with this friend from high school.  He was a spoiled rich kid who had been acting like the classic " ugly American" all throughout our tour of the continent after our high school graduation.  I think he felt inferior being in older, foreign cities more culture than our shallow, suburban and corporate US culture and had to act superior to everyone to compensate for his inferiority complex.<br><br>My friend asked why I was talking to such a fellow.  I said that he was insightful and joked about how punk rock unites humanity.  My friend scoffed.  I said that at least instead of hating his brothers across the English Channel he was united with other punks who hated elitism and the wars that king's, priests and politicians have always created.  It was perfect irony, his coarse attitude coupled with an inward sensitivity.  I said that if I would have been in my grandfather's reality in the 1940s as an American in Germany then the punk and I would have been shooting at each other. "How much could these people have changed in 50 years?  God damn Nazis," he said with a scornful laugh.  "You did not think the girls on the train were god damned Nazis," I responded.<br><br>Later that night after getting settled in our hotel and dining we were out walking.  There was some loud dance music and a line if people outside what seemed to be a club.  They were all stylish people, a little older than us, most in their twenties or thirties.  My friend wanted to go check it out.  I was not interested and said that I was dressed in a wind breaker while all of the people they were all decked out in really cool clothes.  The jacket I used was actually my friend's.  He was wearing a nice and even stylish coat of mine and asked me to trade coats with him for the night.  He insisted we try and get in and dragged me over.  He asked some other people around our age what the place was.  They said it was one of the coolest places in town and had been waiting an hour to get in.  My friend asked why it took so long and the young German explained that there were two way mirrors in which the staff there could see who was waiting outside.  If they thought people were cool enough they would open the doors and point at specific people and tell them to come in.  <br><br>I nudged my friend and said this was all so stupid, that there was no way that I would ever get in there even if I wanted to.  He insisted that we try.  <br><br>A few minutes later some really elitist looking man dressed in an all black suit opens the door and points at me to enter the club.  I was surprised and laughed to my friend.  I asked the guy in the door if my friend could enter with me.  He scanned him critically from head to toe and nodded his head in a negating, arrogant manner.  I said thanks anyway but I won't go in without my friend and walked away.  The guy at the door told the rest of the thirty or forty people that nobody else could enter and that they should get going.</p>
<p><br>My friend tried to laugh it off but I was afraid he felt rejected.  Nowadays I would say it was definitely a good think to have false dreams rudely broken so as to wake up and get real but at that time I still did not have such clarity and confidence and felt bad for my friend.  I felt ashamed.  I  was not sure why at the time but felt that it was all such an ugly experience; all of those sycophants who bend like a willow trying to get accepted by such an ignorant and superficial elite.  Who put them in charge?  Why do they decide things?  I recalled the punk I met earlier and reflected on how he was much more real than the rest of the people I met that day.  <br><br>So I told my friend that we should go back to the train station and find my punk friend.  He could bring his buddies and we could smash some beer bottles outside the club and paint some vulgar insults a on the two way mirrors.  At least my friend laughed a little.<br><br>Exclusivity is so destructive, especially when groups of powerful people prop themselves up by putting down others.  Although the people in the club were so frivolous and superficial, their attitude is found in so many exclusive circles.  If one is shrewd then other shrewd people invite you into their circles where one eventually risks getting devours by them when you are no longer useful.  It is the same with intellectual and artistic pride as well.  I have known some humble and even-minded artists and intellectuals but many artists are full of vanity and driven by ambition and a sense of superiority.   I even think that most spirituality is just rude vanity masked by tranquility and sham humility.  They will also use their two way mirrors and invite you into their circles only to eventually devour you when you try to be yourself.<br><br>Whatever one does one must be sincere.  To be sincere is to be humble.  Humility is not weakness.  It is a strength acquired through so many struggles to put the fearful and isolated ego aside and permit the consciousness of the universe to work inside oneself and bestow some of its array infinite qualities into your personal expression.  This process is part of our inward evolution and all beings will eventually have to tread this path of integrity.  The Atman is the only true and honest mirror that we have.  It does not judge nor distort our true, inner image.  Perhaps it is difficult to see in this light of truth for a mind accustomed to darkness, but its process of integrating the wayward mind towards Consciousness is always for our welfare.  <br><br>Such vain and self serving attitudes are everywhere and are the roots of racism, classism, nationalism and all of the other "isms" that I find so shallow and stupid.  Human societies are mostly just silly popularity circles run by little princess and princesses who are so lost and lonely that they bandy together with other lost souls who think they have some superior qualities they can suppress others with.  The shrewd elite are really weak and fearful people who can never look into their inner mirror and walk a path of integrity.  I recall the Sex Pistols and the German punk reciting them:  "They made you a moron".. and "there is no future for you"......  <br><br>Truly there is no future for a humanity dominated by such ideas and our arrogance is destroying the entire planet.  Vanity and exclusivity are behind racism, economic and class exploitation and so many materialistic distortions that are destroying nature and humanity.  These are very disturbing realities that unquiet the minds of most thoughtful people I know.  I think that they would despair if they were not sincerely trying to help others and create a better world.  Yet sometimes the most optimistic minds are overwhelmed. Perhaps as an escape for myself I conjure the memory of the punk shouting the refrain "no future for you..." as  the rude lyrics of  God Save The Queen resound in the mind as a mantra to drown out these far ruder impressions.<br><br>Two Israelis Under The Atman<br><br>However, the universal spirit, or Atman, never gives up on us.  It is the nucleus consciousness of the entire universe.  It is the "prime mover" of all physical, mental and spiritual dimensions of the universe.  The human mind unconsciously seeks its source in infinite consciousness.  Our higher ideas and sentiments are designed to lead us into union with this essence.  As it is the universal consciousness within every mind, every mind must eventually express subtler consciousness.  Sensible and conscientious people all over the planet have an intuition of the One that unites us all. <br><br>There was a short period in which I would leave my abode in the desert and make short trips.  Mostly I met indigenous people while visiting their communities, but also people from many places in the world.  At that time I was meditating a lot and lived a very quiet and contemplative existence.   I preferred this over the active life in cities but I really enjoyed getting out and meeting people from time to time.  Really, a great part of meditation is being able to truly connect with others.  Obstacles and staticity always intrude on one´s spiritual practice that is based solely on the individual desire for liberation.  If the Atman is found within one, then, by its very nature, it must also be seen in others.  Seeing the divinity in other people is just as important as finding the divinity within.  <br><br>I was once in San Cristobal De Las Casas, Chiapas.  A friend had referred two young Israeli men to me because she thought they would like to talk to me about meditation and yoga.  They had just finished the compulsory military tour of duties.  They were in Gaza during one of the most violent periods around ten or twelve years ago.  Any world traveller comes across Israeli soldiers who are travelling the world after they are discharged.  They are so often traumatised and looking for ways to anaesthetise their pain with drugs and alcohol or some other escape.  Sure, there were some who found more healthy ways of escape by simply travelling and seeing the world but it was all too common to find circles of ex soldiers living in some place like India where hash or heroin was really cheap and one could live for years with scant savings after military service.  <br><br>The two young men I met were very special.  They were traveling, had been to Africa and South America and were now in Mexico.  They had already passed through the scenes of raves, alcohol and ecstasy but were still unsatisfied and looking for something more. They smoked some weed and enjoyed some novel reflections on life before being haunted by violent memories that no substance could quell. They told me they were looking for a shaman to give them ayahuascar or peyote.  <br><br>One of them was very cool and calm.  It surprised me to see that he had such peace in him after I later heard what he had been through.  The other was more expressive and outgoing.  He had a certain intensity about him but had an extremely sharp mind that he could withdraw from its intensity to reflect upon deep ideas.  He told me very clearly that they had tried everything they thought could help them but simply have not found an escape.....They must find some sort of escape.<br><br>The vocal one told me that he was in Gaza just a few months before our meeting.  He told me that he had to confront some Palestinian militants who were using a small child as a shield.  They pointed a weapon at the Israeli soldiers while holding a child in front of them so that the soldiers would not shoot them.  I did not ask him what he did nor did he tell me.  He said the Palestinians were terrorists.  His friend interjected and said that they had really given them no other choice, that his country´s political policies creates terrorism. They were also terrorist, he said.   <br><br>I told them that I was also from an imperialist, terrorist culture.  The United States used slaves to build the country while killing off the indigenous people.  I would feel terrible shame if I had any national pride or waved a flag. Being a human was so much more than all of those lies and those morons who believed in such things were really not yet humans.  This is the planet of the apes, I said, and then apologised to the apes for the insult of bringing them down to our level.  <br><br>I responded to him by saying they want to escape into something that they do not have in order to get rid of what they have.  I said maybe you can find something that you already have to help you git rid of what you do not want.  They both followed me and knew I was speaking of something spiritual.  The outspoken one said with desperate intensity, "How?, Where is it?  <br><br>It is closer to you than your deepest thought or your most traumatic memory, I responded.  I spoke of the Witness of the mind that is always consciously present and aware of the mind in an eternal presence.  It is with us in heaven and hell, in joy and suffering.  It is above the activities of the mind but always attracts it toward its higher essence where all of the relative doubts and suffering can find relief, can find a meaning and reason.  You just have to find a way to still the mind to see that your awareness just is, that it continues even when you are not thinking or feeling or acting.  It is a joyful experience and if you experience it just a little the mind finds some happiness, a little bit of light begins to creep into its labyrinths and whispers a few secrets and inspirations of how to heal.  <br><br>The calm one sat there so calm like he already knew this.  The other one vocalised and conceptualised it a little.  "Yes, it is always there and never changes...I know it is there but it is too easy to forget and I do not know how to get back...is this where we were or where we came from when we were children?"<br><br>The Atman is the ground of our awareness.  It is like the electricity passing through a series of different bulbs.  The light might be white, yellow, or blue, may be a disco ball or a lava lamp, but no matter what form the outlet expressing it has, it is always the same electricity enlightening all.  It is one struggle to see it in oneself, but an even greater struggle to see it in others, especially those who are perceived to be the enemy.  To find some common ground in the social and relative world between rivals is peace.  But what if those social negotiations also recognised a deeper common ground?  Would there be a god of Israel, a god of Islam, or the god of the Christians to impede our essential union?</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>All Of Us</title>
        <author>
            <name>William Enckhausen</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://williamenck.art/all-of-us/"/>
        <id>https://williamenck.art/all-of-us/</id>

        <updated>2025-03-11T18:57:57-06:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Meister Eckhart once wrote that the essence of all creatures is nothingness. At other times he said that the human soul was at one with the Godhead, that there is no essential separation of the human soul from God. I believe these are different ways&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://williamenck.art/media/posts/36/ernst.jpg" alt="" width="1380" height="1021" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://williamenck.art/media/posts/36/responsive/ernst-xs.jpg 640w ,https://williamenck.art/media/posts/36/responsive/ernst-sm.jpg 768w ,https://williamenck.art/media/posts/36/responsive/ernst-md.jpg 1024w ,https://williamenck.art/media/posts/36/responsive/ernst-lg.jpg 1366w ,https://williamenck.art/media/posts/36/responsive/ernst-xl.jpg 1600w ,https://williamenck.art/media/posts/36/responsive/ernst-2xl.jpg 1920w"></figure><br>Meister Eckhart once wrote that the essence of all creatures is nothingness.  At other times he said that the human soul was at one with the Godhead, that there is no essential separation of the human soul from God.  I believe these are different ways of expressing the unity of all spirits and their essential divinity.  Only as separated beings are we nothingness.  Separation is nothingness because it is not real.  It is very similar to the yogic idea of the unity of the Atman (individual soul) and Brahman (the universal soul). A yogi meditates on the idea that any form of individuality separate from the whole is nothing but self-spun delusion based in fear and mundane desire.    Realizing the bliss of unity with the infinite is the only way to liberate oneself from this incessant suffering and nothingness.  Such mystical realizations that liberate one from the relative world can also help one to create new ideas in this relative world.  Instead of abandoning this world for some transcendental form of bliss beyond the world, our spiritual efforts can help us break down all of the personal and social barriers that keep us trapped in our separateness, suffering, and alienation.  True happiness consists of trying to help others find happiness as well.  While striving for personal liberation we are also striving for collective liberation in that we redirect our will towards self realization and stop participating in narrow, selfish and destructive patterns that destroy human society and the planet we live on.  Instead of living for selfish ends we begin to live for the well-being of all because we are each the all. <br><br>The idea of the universal, spiritual, human family is a pure essence beyond any social or organizational manifestation of this idea.  As a universal idea, it can sprout in any heart and mind anywhere, yet cannot be patented by any one group or individual.  The idea is embedded in the essence of the Godhead, the source of all divine creation, to use this term of Meister Eckhart's (which is a term used by other Christian mystics as well).  <br><br>Personally, I  have come to deeply mistrust organized religion and spirituality.  The best examples of universal love that I have seen have emanated by strong individuals who are not selfish in their individuality and truly think of and act for the welfare of others.  Spiritual societies often give one a place in the human social world and hopefully teach one how to behave but rarely propel one toward mystical realization or revolutionary actions.  Perhaps sincere expressions of universal love have existed in certain religions at certain times.  These expressions are very relative and often do not endure before they are tainted by some sectarian superiority complex which eventually leads to downfall, hypocrisy and degeneration.  <br><br>I had a few friends and students who entered a yoga society even though I told them about the problems with that group.  I do not blame them because I tend to agree with the philosophy and spiritual ideals of the movement and met some really sincere people who manifested these ideals.  That was a long time ago, and the situation has entirely changed, yet I did tell them that it was all once real despite what has happened.  It is understandable, their joining this society:  being all on one's own practicing yoga, meditating, and being vegetarian makes one bit of a social outcast.  It is only natural to want to seek fellowship and inspiration with like-minded aspirants.  For the sake of upholding a great ideal I would participate in such a society if it did not require me to be incongruous and distort reality by trying to rationalize too much hypocrisy.  <br><br>So if one cannot depend on some existing society, one must retreat into essence and find the oneness of the soul in all beings, not just humans but in all forms of life.  Existing in a state of spiritual unity with other beings is true society and connection with others, even if conventionally minded people do not understand.  It is better and more wholesome to exist in truthfulness with a few than to co-exist in great lies that many believe in.  Yet existing with kindness and compassion is felt by others and helps breaks down our artificial, self-spun separation at least a little.   Even the most mean minded people are capable of awakening.   And if more people awakened spiritual consciousness in their lives, then we would have more possibility of creating a human society based in spiritual consciousness.  If certain individuals can evolve into more sensitive and conscious beings then it is a possibility that the rest of the species can also, in time, make this leap.  And what better time than now with the planet in such a precarious state?  It is a do or die situation. We must evolve or be extinguished.  Seeing the essential divinity in all is the universal panacea for all of the troubles that plague this planet.  By being more conscious one becomes consciousness, and this consciousness extends in to every one and everything.  One's mind becomes a laser that penetrates and burns through the distortions in the collective consciousness, thus breaking down the collective obstacles little by little.  The vital notion of the conscious, human family can break down all forms of rigid and violent nationalism and racism, lessen social disparities, and unify all societies.  Extending this spiritual sentiment into the non human world and into nature will heal all of our environmental imbalances as well.<br><br>For an informed and rational mind it is very difficult to have optimism in these times.  The planet is literally burning up with record breaking droughts, heat waves, flooding and forest fires.  The human social world is on fire with the threat of another world war with the conflict in Ukraine and also with the tensions between China and the West.   And all the while the entire world is slipping into economic recession.  <br><br>On the morning before the news of the Russian invasion of Ukraine I had a spiritual experience while waking from sleep.  I felt the kundalini rising up my spine and my sense of self disappeared into a tunnel of light.  I could still feel my physical chest where the kundalini had risen, in the Anahata spiritual heart.  There hardly remained any notion of physical forms, just light and pulsating, flowing energy that radiated through the Anahata out into the entire universe.  It was infinite bliss and if the experience would have continued any longer  I am certain I would have left my physical body once and for all.  My heart was at one with the energetic heart of the Macrocosm.  The only thought and words that came into my mind during this experience were "thank you" repeating over and over again.  I woke up and there was hell on earth:  Russia had invaded Ukraine, there were droughts and floods and heat-waves over the entire planet.  <br><br>I recalled my first kundalini experiences that I had in my last year in the university.  I hardly was able to finish my studies due to their intensity.  I lost all interest in worldly pursuits and only wanted to dissolve in the infinite light that I was experiencing.  These awakenings continued for several years with great intensity.  Many of my monastic friends said that I would die before I was 30 or 40 because such experiences take on so far beyond the physical world and the mind immersed in spirit loses parallelism with the body.  Yet I found other adventures to keep me grounded in the world.  <br><br>These experiences returned to me again years later while I was in the desert fending off the narcos from our community.  I wrote in the essay,<a href="https://filedn.eu/lJ2nfF6TS2qfy9gLlLonYGy/a-requiem"> A Requiem</a>, about how when the narcos came for me one night with a chainsaw outside of my house.  I heard the chainsaw start up but then I started to hear the Om sound with its infinite bliss and the Om sound became so loud it drowned out the sound of the chainsaw.  I entirely forgot about the narcos as I was in a trance for several hours.  When I returned to bodily consciousness I was fine, with all of my limbs still intact!  The kundalini is indeed a divine force, the seed of the Macrocosmic divinity within the human microcosm.  The kundalini created a spiritual shield during those intense years of fighting off the narco assassins. There was death and horror all around but internally everything was in harmony. <br><br>I still am not sure about why these experiences occurred again recently but when news about this hellish world makes me miserable I remember these experiences and never forget the words of Anandamurti which have proven so true time after time:  "The Supreme Consciousness is always with you, even in hell."</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>White Trash</title>
        <author>
            <name>William Enckhausen</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://williamenck.art/white-trash/"/>
        <id>https://williamenck.art/white-trash/</id>

        <updated>2025-03-11T18:56:08-06:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    People are essentially the same everywhere. Only externally we appear so different. Everywhere you go in the world you find the same basic virtues as well as the same scandals. Human beings create the same gods and devils all around the globe. Perhaps the particular&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__image">People are essentially the same everywhere. Only externally we appear so different. Everywhere you go in the world you find the same basic virtues as well as the same scandals. Human beings create the same gods and devils all around the globe. Perhaps the particular society in which one lives follows cyclical paths of ups and downs and the people rise and fall accordingly, but it always happens to human beings in very similar ways. Only political and materialistic opportunists who promote fear in the ignorant and fearful people focus more on people´s differences than people´s similarities. Nationalism, even in more responsible and rational forms, has always seemed rather immature compared to the idea that we are all microcosmic consciousness evolving and existing in the living and vibrant Macrocosmic Consciousness of the universe.  <br>  <br>The subjective Consciousness is the same in all beings. We may have different minds, but the internal "I" is identical in all. It is only in the objective part of our minds that we are different. The objective mind (chitta) is connected to the external world and the physical brain and so it therefore is qualified by external objectivity. If one sees only the external, then all appears different. People are simply conditioned and qualified by different environments and objective circumstances like race, culture and social class. However, if one knows the pure, inner Consciousness, then one realizes that the internal, subjective Consciousness is the same in the divine Macrocosm as well as all individual beings, or "microcosms." All beings share the same inner soul with the infinite subjective Consciousness, or Macrocosm.  The microcosm and Macrocosm are essentially united.  Really, there is only a Macrocosmic Mind and Consciousness. "Microcosm" is actually a misnomer; it is used to describe a mind qualified by relative, changing objectivity, the part of one´s subjective consciousness that appears to be qualified and changed by the external world.  Yet this consciousness is never really modified. It is like a mirror reflecting so many objects. No matter how many objects and colors that are reflected in the mirror the mirror never changes.   <br><br>I listened to an interview with Cornel West the other night. I cannot say I have read his works but his interviews have always impressed me. What most illuminated me from this interview were his reflections on how the Neo-liberal Left and the Neo-Fascist Right are controlled by the same big interests in Wall Street and the Military Industrial Complex. Both sides serve the American Empire, only the Left wants to let minorities and women into the game while the Right maintains a more traditional racist attitude. He spoke at length about how people are never introduced, even in universities, to the idea that the U.S. is an empire with a history of colonialism, genocide, and capitalist exploitation.  <br>  <br>Reflecting on this interview I begin to think of a person whose image I always try to keep out of my mind, the “Neo-Fascist” leader that West refers to. I only recently heard his voice and listened to this person speak. I feel at one with world but there are still people whose mental form is so disturbing that I do not want to let them anywhere near my soul by even thinking of them. When we conjure up a person or object in our minds there is actually a connection with the original object or person. Weak and unconscious minds only see their own projections and have very little connection with the original object in their minds. The stronger and purer the mind, the more one is able to connect with the person.  <br>  <br>Trump is the supreme and perfect example of “white trash.” “White trash” is a term I stopped using some time ago, at least until now. It seemed rather racist in that it implies that white people can also be “trash,” not just the minorities so commonly discriminated against. Also, its common use to describe rural and simple folk is truly offensive. I cannot even use the term "white trash" for fearful and violent, gun-slinging fundamentalist Christians.  These people have inferiority complexes that are exploited by their leaders who inject a false sense of national and racial superiority.  I can only call their leaders "white trash."  Trump is the perfect symbol of collective ignorance and brutality, the perfect leader for a trash culture in a trash empire. Only trashy, crude, materialistic consciousness could manifest this abomination.  <br><br><img loading="lazy"  src="https://williamenck.art/media/posts/35/white-trash.jpg" alt="" width="976" height="549" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://williamenck.art/media/posts/35/responsive/white-trash-xs.jpg 640w ,https://williamenck.art/media/posts/35/responsive/white-trash-sm.jpg 768w ,https://williamenck.art/media/posts/35/responsive/white-trash-md.jpg 1024w ,https://williamenck.art/media/posts/35/responsive/white-trash-lg.jpg 1366w ,https://williamenck.art/media/posts/35/responsive/white-trash-xl.jpg 1600w ,https://williamenck.art/media/posts/35/responsive/white-trash-2xl.jpg 1920w"></figure>  <br>Such distortions of human consciousness that endanger our evolution are always eventually cursed by nature and the Macrocosm itself turns against them. Nature simply unleashes all of the accumulated reactions to the past actions of the collective consciousness with such perfect precision and even uncanny symbolism so as to make it clear to history that what was destroyed was an abomination. Hopefully, now I can remove this form from my mind but I do in some strange way thank Trump for beings such a clear and perfect symbol. The American Empire will not be spared the fate of other fallen empires who no longer serve any evolutionary purpose.  <br>  <br>I recently dreamed that I was hiking to the North Pole with ex-president Obama.  He was asking me some questions about yoga philosophy.  I did not want to talk to him.  I thought internally that "you might be a decent fellow if you weren´t the leader of the corporate empire, the war machine of the military industrial complex, etc.etc....  I said nothing.    <br>  <br>In the dream I was aware it was a dream and was thinking I am dreaming this because in my past, after the Purulia incident, I was always in playful dialogues with very "intelligent" people.   <a href="https://filedn.eu/lJ2nfF6TS2qfy9gLlLonYGy/the-debate/">I had an eye kept on me but I was an innocent person in the debacle</a> and I felt that the intelligence and military people I dialogued with were genuinely friendly with me.  They knew I was no patriot but also understood that I was not an anarchist or violent revolutionary.  I took advantage of the situation to give them some subtle moral clashes about being servants of the war machine.  I wondered that if they woke up a little spiritually and morally if they would end up renouncing their government and military positions?  For example, I once dialoged with a navy officer and West Point professor about neo-platonic ideas and their similarity with the Upanashadic doctrine of the identity of the Atman with Brahman.  This is essentiall the same debate of the Christian mystics as to if the human soul is at one with and identical to God, or if it was a separate entity than the divine essence.  He cited John Scotus Eriugena.  We spoke about whether the Atman, the individual soul, was equal to Brahman, the universal soul.  I said it was true and he asked if it were true in the sense of the two cantaloupes he was holding were identical.  Are they identical, or just similar?, he asked.  I said that there is nothing exactly similar in the physical plane but in the spirit all is one.  It would be as if two cantaloupes could be exactly identical.  If they were completely identical then we could not notice their separateness under any scrutiny and they would be entirely one.  Such coincidence is impossible in the physical world but in the spirit all is one.  However, in the physical world we should see unity in diversity, as finite and diverse creation trying to express the Infinite through the evolution of consciousness, I said.  <br>  <br>Anyway, it was my personal little history of being able to see how people inside the both sides of the eternal game of rebels and empire officials really think, as human beings.  And so with this in my mind I realised that this was the reason that in this dream I was supposed to guide him to the north pole.  Obama in this dream is definitely the most refined symbol of great human intellect enslaved to dirty politics, in the end a false humane and rational face for the most irrational and self-destructive empire.    <br>  <br>Continuing with the dream, we reached the tip of the world.  The North Pole was directly in the middle of what seemed to be an igloo.  On approaching it closer the igloo was really a pool.  It was covered from the weather and there was a small door on this roof to enter the waters below.  Obama asked me to open it.  I saw the waters were deep and connected to the oceans all around this block of ice we were standing on top of.  Obama asked to look in and I moved aside.  The waters started swirling and the entire pool became a giant vortex.  A giant wave engulfed him and I watched him get flushed.  The vortex grew and engulfed the entire north pole and I saw the entire human society getting flushed as well.  I was wondering why I was not getting flushed but realised I was just a witness without a physical body in this dream.  <br>  <br>Rightist, leftist; capitalist, communist:  If your philosophy is matter then in the end you really do not matter.  Matter is an illusion, people only believe in it when their spiritual heart is not yet open.  Universal reason cannot be separated from universal love.    <br>  <br>Over the last 500 years it has been demonstrated that the capitalist system cannot survive without genocide, slavery, and a multinational imperialism which exploits human labor and hoards natural resources stolen from other lands. Communism, which was born as the bastard son and counter-reaction to capitalism, has mostly fallen short of its ideals when put into practice. Instead of a liberated proletariat and the dissolution of the state, we find tyrannical central governments that grossly oppress human rights. Capitalism seeks to bind with gold chains while communism binds with heavy iron chains. Neither system helps all of humanity evolve physically, mentally, or spiritually.  <br>  <br>If there are parasites that attack the physical organism, then why cannot there exist parasites that attack the mental organism? Just as parasites can root their way into an imbalanced and infirm organism, then why could not a mental parasite worm its way into an infirm mind, or ideologies that create mental imbalances? Perhaps limited, materialistic ideas like capitalism and communism are destined to make both the individual and collective minds insane because they are limited ideologies based on materialism and only recognise the material and social nature of human beings. A human being desires infinite freedom. Not only do we desire freedom, but we are designed to seek it. There exist within us all of the thought forms and emotional structures to seek higher mental and spiritual forms of happiness. The common error is to seek the infinite in the finite. If our infinite desires situate themselves exclusively in creature comforts and egocentric desires, then frustration and unhappiness will eventually destroy this limited happiness as one´ś higher nature has not been expressed.  <br>  <br>These mental parasites are called microvita in tantra yoga. Just like there are positive as well as negative bacterias, there are both positive and negative microvita. Positive microvita stimulate the higher desires of the mind and the endocrine system while negative microvita keep the mind bound to our animal nature. There is always a balance of positive and negative microvita in nature but when negative microvita become overly expressed and positive microvita are not expressed, then great imbalances occur and nature must restore order. A human being that does not participate in physical, mental and spiritual evolution is a waste of energy and will be attacked by negative microvita. The planet must get rid of some dead weight. Ideologies that mold human beings into slaves of matter will eventually be flushed by nature as they do not foster the evolution of spirit.  <br>  <br>The mind is the intermediary entity between spirit and matter. "As you think, so you become." The mind becomes like the objects of its attachments. Subtle occupations of the mind make the mind finer while crude occupations degrade the mind. If the ego, the driver of the mind, is weak then negative microvita help make one selfish and mean minded, seeks creature comforts and dreams of getting rich, and attaining only mundane ambitions. If one is strong and intelligent then positive microvita helps one to struggle for liberation from all mental limitations and ultimately finds peace in the infinite spirit within. When the mind unifies with spirit it is nirvana, freedom from time and rebirth. The mind no longer exists as a separate entity: it merges into spirit. When one defies one´s true purpose of dharma (the path of physical and mental evolution toward spiritual freedom) the mind unifies with matter. In this union one is also free from human rebirth: the mind disintegrates in matter, the body dies, and one becomes one with the garbage on the streets and the caca in the sewers.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
